A Finding Aid to the Erle Loran Papers, 1912-1999, in the Archives of American Art AAA.loraerle
Archives of American Art
Erle Loran papers
1912-1999
AAA.loraerle
Archives of American Art
12.6 Linear feet
The papers of California painter, writer, and teacher Erle Loran measure 12.6 linear feet and date from 1912 to 1991. Found are biographical materials; two linear feet of personal and professional correspondence; personal business records; writings which include extensive drafts and notes for Loran's book Cezanne's Composition; over 400 items of artwork that include watercolors, drawings, charcoal, and pastel studies; printed materials; photographs of Loran, family, and friends, and artwork; and one audio recording of a lecture by Loran on Cezanne.
Loran, Erle, 1905-1999
Provenance
Erle Loran donated much of the material in 1975. His widow Ruth Schora-Loran donated additional papers, including the artwork in 1999.
Separated Material
Photographs of artwork by Erle Loran and two clippings of reproductions of Erle Loran's artwork were loaned for microfilming in 1975 and are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 906 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. These materials are not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
Found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Erle Loran conducted by Herschel Chipp, June 18, 1981, and a 1981 interview with Erle and Clyta Loran in the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco Interviews With Artists collection. Also found is a letter from Loran to Richard Wattenmaker, 1975.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
California painter, writer, and teacher Erle Loran was born on October 2, 1905 in Minneapolis, Minnesota. He attended the Minneapolis School of Art and graduated in 1926. That same year, Loran won the Paris Prize from the Chaloner Foundation which enabled him to study in France for the next three years. Here, he immersed himself into the world of Paul Cezanne. He lived for two years in Cézanne's studio, meeting many who knew Cezanne, including painter Emile Bernard, and art dealer Ambroise Vollard. This experience was critical to the development of Loran's artistic vision and his later writings and lectures about Cézanne.
In 1929, Loran returned to the United States, and published the article "Cézanne's Country" in The Arts in 1930. He then spent the early 1930s in Minnesota, after returning to Minneapolis to be treated for tuberculosis. There, Loran began to paint in a regionalist style, producing landscapes and scenes of life in rural Minnesota. In 1931, Loran was given his first one-man show at the Kraushaar Gallery in New York. During the depression, Loran began teaching art and was given painting commissions as part of the federal arts programs of the WPA.
Loran moved to California in 1937 and accepted a position as professor in the art department at the University of California, Berkeley. There he taught until retiring in 1973, serving as the department's chair in the 1950s. He established a program to invite east coast artists to teach at the university, and participants included Conrad Marca-Relli and Milton Resnick. Loran's students included Jay DeFeo, Richard Diebenkorn, and Sam Francis. In 1941 Loran began to write the synthesis of his research and interpretations about Cézanne's work, culminating in his pioneering book Cézanne's Composition published in 1943 by the University of California Press.
During this period Loran associated himself with modernist Hans Hoffman. Loran's early paintings were lyrical abstractions in primary colors; however, his style constantly changed with the times. Watercolor was Loran's medium of choice because it lent itself to his often-remote plein air locations, such as the ghost towns of California and Nevada. With John Haley and Worth Ryder he formed the "Berkeley Group," whose paintings consisted of scenes of the California and southwestern landscape painted in flat, open areas of color. During the war, painting in the open became increasingly difficult and Loran transitioned from plein-air painting to studio work. Shortly thereafter he began to focus his painting on abstraction.
Loran's artwork during the 1950s consisted primarily of abstractions based on natural forms like crystal and driftwood. In 1955, he spent six weeks studying with Hans Hofmann, whom he later called, along with Cézanne, a second "great father figure." In 1960, he was instrumental in securing a gift of forty-five paintings by Hans Hofmann for Berkeley's University Art Center. In the late 1960s, his work became a fusing of Op, Pop, and Hard Edge. From this he moved to figurative painting and later to geometric designs and symbols.
Loran continued to paint throughout the rest of his life in a variety of styles, including nudes, abstractions, and landscapes. Besides being an artist and a teacher, Loran was also a lifelong collector of ethnic art who specialized in African, Asian, Native American, and pre-Columbian tribal art. Many works from his collection are presently housed at the de Young Museum in San Francisco. Loran died in 1999 in Berkeley, at the age of 93.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of California painter and teacher Erle Loran measure 12.6 linear feet and date from 1912 to 1991. Found are biographical materials; two linear feet of personal and professional correspondence; personal business records; writings which include extensive drafts and notes for Loran's book Cezanne's Composition; over 400 items of artwork that include watercolors, drawings, charcoal, and pastel studies; printed materials; photographs of Loran, family, and friends, and artwork; and one audio recording of a lecture by Loran on Cezanne.
Biographical materials include biographical sketches, curriculum vita, a will, notes and a notebook, and an appointment book for 1987. Also found is an anniversary invitation, a certificate from the University of California, and the Pepsi-Cola award for 1948.
Two linear feet of correspondence is with artists, critics, galleries, and universities. Correspondents inlcude Romare Bearden, Andrew Dasburg, Clement Greenberg, John Haley, Dalzell Hatfield, Hans Hofmann, Harry Levinson (president of Permanent Pigments), Sam Sabean, Bertha Schaefer, Clyfford Still, and Ulfert Wilke. There is also correspondence with the University of California.
Personal business records include exhibition files, price and consignment lists, teaching materials, University of California Press records, and records relating to the publication of his book on Cézanne. Some of these records also document Loran's involvement with the Fine Arts Museum, Friends of Ethnic Arts, and the San Francisco Art Institute. In addition, there are records related to Loran's role in a donation of forty-five paintings by Hans Hofmann to the University Art Center. Also found are materials related to Loran's activities as an art collector including sales receipts, auction catalogs, and photographs of artwork owned by Loran.
Writings by Loran include a complete manuscript version of Cézanne's Composition along with additional notes and drafts, and numerous other short essays on Cézanne's life and art. Loran's other writings include essays about Hans Hofmann, Marsden Hartley, symbology in abstract art, and contemporary art.
Loran's career as an artist is extensively documented by four linear feet of original artwork, mostly preliminary sketches. The work demonstrates a variety of techniques including watercolor, pastel, pencil, pen, gouache, and oil sketches. Content includes landscapes, portraits, fantasy scenes, urban scenes, and rural scenes.
Printed materials include extensive newsclippings from seven decades, exhibition announcements, and exhibition catalogs. Photographs are of Loran, his second wife Clyta, the Loran family, friends and colleagues, artwork, and source materials. Also found within the papers is an audio recording on cassette of a lecture by Loran on Cézanne.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1930s-1990s (Box 1; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1912-1992 (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1930s-1992 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1921-1999 (Boxes 3-4; 1.25 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, 1920s-1980s (Boxes 4-8, 13-14; 4.3 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1925-1999 (Boxes 8-10, 14; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Photographs, 1910s-1990s (Boxes 10-12, 14; 2.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Audio Recording, 1982 (Box 12; 1 folder)
Bearden, Romare, 1911-1988; Cézanne, Paul, 1839-1906; Dasburg, Andrew, 1887-1979; Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco; Friends of Ethnic Art; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994; Haley, John, 1905-1991; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943; Hatfield, Dalzell, 1893-1963; Hofmann, Hans, 1880-1966; Levinson, Harry; Sabean, Samuel; San Francisco Art Institute; Schaefer, Bertha, 1895-1971; Still, Clyfford, 1904-; University of California, Berkeley. -- Faculty; Wilke, Ulfert, 1907-1987; Art teachers--California--Berkeley; Art, Abstract; Art, Modern--20th century; Art--Collectors and collecting--California--San Francisco Bay Area; Painters--California--Berkeley; Painting, Modern--20th century--California--Berkeley; Photographs; Sketches; Watercolors; Writings
- Biographical Materials, 1930s-1990s; Series 1; (Box 1; 0.25 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes biographical sketches, a biographical questionnaire, curriculum vita, a notebook, medical records, a handwritten copy of Loran's will, and Loran's 1948 Pepsi-Cola Achievement Award. His personal and professional activities for 1987 are recorded in great detail in an appointment book. Also found is a floor plan for the Lorans' home. Material related to the Loran family includes a certificate commemorating Clyta Loran's work for the University of California, and an invitation to a family event.
  - Addresses, 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anniversary Invitation, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Book, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Questionnaire, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Sketches, 1930s-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business Card, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certificate, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1952-1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Deed of Gift, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Entry Cards, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Floor Plans, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Maps, circa 1930s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Medical Materials, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notebook, circa 1950s-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pepsi-Cola Award, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Will, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1912-1992; Series 2; (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
  Voluminous correspondence is related to Loran's activities as an artist and educator, as well as personal and family affairs. Correspondence is with family, friends, artists, educators, writers, gallery owners, and others. Correspondents include Donald Bear, Romare Bearden, Andrew Dasburg, Stuart Davis, Jay DeFeo, Walter De Maria, Richard Diebenkorn, Alfred Frankenstein, Clement Greenberg, Louis Guglielmi, John Haley, Dalzell Hatfield, Thomas Hess, Hans Hofmann, Carl Holty, Jules Langsner, Harry Levinson (president of Permanent Pigments), George McNeil, John Rewald, Daniel Canton Rich, Samuel Sabean, Bertha Schaefer, Hassel Smith, Clyfford Still, Francis Henry Taylor, and Ulfert Wilke, among many others. Also found are eight folders of sympathy cards received upon Clyta Loran's death in 1982.
  - A-An, 1948-1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - An-Ay, 1916-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alcopley, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Appreciation Card, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Archives of American Art, 1966-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Artforum, 1962-1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - B-Be, 1941-1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Be-By, 1944-1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Donald Bear, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Romare Bearden, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - C-Ch, 1944-1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cl-Cr, 1945-1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lee Carlson, 1968-1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Herman Cherry, 1960-1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Fred Clayton, 1925-1946 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bruce Conner, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Bruce Cunningham, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bruce Cunningham, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bruce Cunningham, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bruce Cunningham, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - D-Di, 1943-1981 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Di-Du, 1957-1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Alfred Dasburg, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Andrew Dasburg, 1953-1971 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Stuart Davis, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Jay DeFeo, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Walter De Maria, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Richard Diebenkorn, 1952-1977 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - C.V. Donovan, 1960-1982 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - E, 1947-1975 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - F-Fi, 1948-1986 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Fi-Fu, 1943-1981 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Claire Falkenstein, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Dory Flodin, 1947-1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Alfred Frankenstein, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Helen Frankenthaler, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - G-Gl, 1926-1982 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Gl-Gu, 1942-1981 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Clement Greenberg, 1944-1952 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Louis Guglielmi, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - H-Hi, 1938-1985 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hi-Hu, 1947-1987 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - John and Monica Haley, 1940-1980 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Dalzell and Ruth Hatfield, 1945-1979 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Thomas Hess, 1951-1965 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Hans Hofmann, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Holiday Cards, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Carl Holty, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Walter Horn, 1958-1976 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - I, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Robert Bruce Inverarity, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Miyo Ito, 1954-1982 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - J, 1924-1993 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Ruth Johnson, 1960-1991 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Walter Johnson, 1912-1952 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Ynez Johnston, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - K, 1941-1991 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Karl Kasten, 1957-1989 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Clark Kerr, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Irving Kriesberg, 1966-1989 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Katherine Kuh, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - L, 1943-1982 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Stuart Davis, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Henry Levinson, 1942-1959 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Henry Levinson, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Henry Levinson, 1963-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Roy Lichtenstein, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ward Lockwood, 1952-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clyta Loran, 1956-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Loran Family, circa 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - M-Mar, 1944-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mar-May, 1944-1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mc-Me, 1942-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mi-Mu, 1944-1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Knud Merrild, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Kyle Morris, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - N-Ne, 1949-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ne-No, 1937-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - O, 1943-1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - P, 1948-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Vincent Price, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Q, 1963-1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - R, 1946-1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John Rewald, 1944-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Antonio Ruvolo, 1964-1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Felix Ruvolo, 1957-1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - S-Sh, 1944-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Si-Sm, 1941-1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - So-Sw, 1947-1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sam Sabean, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sam Sabean, 1944-1965 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sam Sabean, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sam Sabean, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sam Sabean, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Vivian Sabean, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Bertha Schaffer, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Meyer Schapiro, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Tom Seligman, 1974-1991 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Hassel Smith, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Clyfford Still, 1952-1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sympathy Cards, 1982; (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 37-44)
  - T, 1944-1968 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Edgar Taylor, 1944-1968 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - U, 1948-1983 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1947-1981 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - University of California Press, 1947-1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - V, 1944-1982 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Ninfa Valvo, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - John Verral, 1944-1966 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Catherine Viviano, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Ann Voulkos, 1974-1982 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - W, 1948-1990 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Allen Weller, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Glenn Wessels, 1953-1977 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1961-1976 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ulfert Wilke, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Emerson Woelffer, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Y, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Z, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Unknown Correspondents, 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Personal Business Records, 1930s-1992; Series 3; (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)
  Found here are scattered records related to the financial and administrative aspects of Loran's work as an artist and writer. Materials related to Loran's artwork includes consignment forms, exhibition checklists, exhibition schedules, records of gifts, price lists, and exhibition labels. Business records concerning Loran's writings include receipts of royalties, forms and correspondence from the University of California Press, and permission forms. Also found are records documenting Loran's involvement with membership in art organizations, such as the Fine Arts Museum of San Francisco, Friends of Ethnic Art, and the San Francisco Art Institute. Teaching activities are represented by classroom handouts, recommendation forms, and materials related to Hans Hofmann's gift to the University Art Center. Other materials document Loran's personal finances and grant applications.
  - Art Supplies, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bay Area Ethnic Arts Organization, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Book Information, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Business Cards, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Consignment Forms, 1951-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Donations, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Exchanges, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Checklists, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Invitations, 1950s-1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Schedules, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Financial Materials, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Fine Arts Museum Materials, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Fine Arts Museum Materials, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Fine Arts Museum Materials, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Floor Plans, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Friends of Ethnic Arts, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Gifts, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Grant Materials, 1975-1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hans Hofmann Collection, 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Insurance, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Legal Materials, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Loans, 1959-1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Mailing Lists, 1960s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ninfa Valvo Materials, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Object Records, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Permissions, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Price Lists, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Purchases, circa 1950s-1986 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Recommendation Forms, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Rentals, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Rentals, 1965-1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Royalties, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - San Francisco Art Institute Materials, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Statement of Authenticity, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Teaching Materials, 1930s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - University of California Press, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Wall Labels, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Writings, 1921-1999; Series 4; (Boxes 3-4; 1.25 linear feet)
  Found here are writings by Erle Loran and others, many about the life and work of Paul Cézanne, including Loran's notes, drafts, and manuscript version of Cézanne's Composition. Additional writings include Loran's essays on Roy Lichtenstein's appropriation of a diagram from Cézanne's Composition; nine folders of writings on the art and pedagogical ideas of Hans Hofmann; and essays about artists Marsden Hartley, Kyle Morris, Harold Paris, Clyfford Still, and Mark Tobey. Also found are Loran's writings on contemporary art, abstract art, and symbology, as well as artist statements and writings from school.
  Writing by others includes pieces on Cézanne, statements by Hans Hofmann and Clyfford Still, and remembrances of Loran upon his death.
  Arrangement note
  Loran's writings are arranged alphabetically by title or supplied title in brackets, followed by writings by others.
  - Approaches to Art, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - [Art on Campus], 1947 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Artist Statements, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Arts Club Chronicle, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Cézanne, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Cézanne(Seminar Notes), circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Cézanne- the Henry and Rose Pearlman Collection, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Cézanne's Composition, circa 1943; (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 50-57)
  - Cézanne's Composition (Notes and Drafts), circa 1943; (17 folders) (Box 3, Folder 58-74)
  - Cézanne's Composition (Acknowledgments), circa 1943 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Cézanne's Composition (Preface to the Second Edition), circa 1946 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Cézanne's Composition (Preface to the Third Edition), circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Cézanne's Procedure in Painting, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Cézanne's Technique, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Chronicle For Herschel Chipp's Guernica, circa 1988 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Collector Purchases Portrait of Mme. Cézanne by Roy Lichtenstein, circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Constructive Criticism, 1920s (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Destructive Criticism, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - The Discovery of Cézanne's Motif, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Elements of Composition in Drawing and Paintings, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - [Fine Art and Illustration], circa 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Form and Content in the History of Art, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - [Fragments], circa 1950s-1980s; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 88-90)
  - The Gulf Stream and England, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Hans Hofmann, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Harold Persico Paris, circa 1979 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - [High School Writings], 1920s (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Hofmann Symposium, circa 1965 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Hostility, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - How Can We Improve Our High School?, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - How to Solve the Budget Crisis at the Berkeley Art Museum, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Influences on Cézanne, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - John Smith, circa 1920s (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Kyle Morris, circa 1979 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Landscape - Cézanne, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - The Last Fifteen Years in Painting, circa 1960s-1970s; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - [Letter to the Guggenheim], circa 1930s-1940s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - [Letter to New York Times], circa 1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - [Letter to New York Times], 1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)